Home Economists in Business--Chicago Chapter Records
University of Illinois at Chicago
Home Economists in Business--Chicago Chapter Records
1924/1992
University of Illinois at Chicago
Home Economists in Business
5.25 linear feet
This collection primarily reflects the activities of HEIB's Chicago chapter between the years of 1924 and 1992, though some of the material illustrates HEIB's activities on state and national levels as well. Documents in this collection contain information about HEIB's history, mission, membership, projects, and finances.
HEIB
Administrative History of HEIB
Home Economists in Business (HEIB) has its beginnings in 1920 when Mary Keown, along with several other members of the American Home Economics Association, became dissatisfied with the structure of the organization; they believed that the AHEA (now known as the American Association of Family and Consumer Sciences) needed to place a greater emphasis on the relationship between home economics and the corporate world. While they voiced this need for an independent business-related committee at the annual AHEA meeting in Colorado Springs that year, nothing came of this request initially. However, in 1927 Mary Keown, Harriet Emmons, Marie Sellers, Sarah McLeod, and Virginia Barnes continued to rally for such a committee, drafting plans for their proposed organization and drawing up a petition. The success of this petition allowed HEIB to finally, in 1924, become recognized as an official committee of the AHEA. When it was first founded, it consisted of a national group as well as two local groups--one in Chicago and one in New York. Because of the organization's growing membership, however, these local groups have expanded to include San Francisco, Boston, Cleveland, Philadelphia, the Twin Cities, and Washington DC. While the Chicago chapter of HEIB was the only one representing the Midwest in 1926, by 1982 over fifty local chapters were affiliated with HEIB.
During the decades that it was active, HEIB was dedicated to integrating the field of home economics into the larger business world. The members of HEIB made it their goal to place qualified home economists in secure job positions, establish professional standards and make young women aware of educational opportunities that would qualify them for work as home economists in the corporate sphere. HEIB produced a monthly newsletter that kept its members informed about innovations in the field, business opportunities, and changes in membership. Additionally, HEIB hosted speakers, conducted research, administered surveys, sponsored several scholarships, and created workshops designed to foster leadership, communication and marketing skills. The organization also focused its efforts on making more business courses available in schools.
Because HEIB was active for the greater part of the century, it underwent several changes during this time. Originally called Home Economics in Business, its early meetings took place at the various households of its members; the hostess would act as temporary chairman at these meetings. This changed in 1927, however, when Dorothy Knight was elected as HEIB's first official chairman. Soon after, the organization changed its name to Home Economists in Business and later modified its membership requirements, making a bachelors or graduate degree in home economics compulsory. Changes were even taking place as late as 1982 when HEIB accepted its first male member. Despite HEIB's evolution, however, it has always remained committed to forming solid relationships between the field of home economics and the larger corporate world.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily reflects the activities of HEIB's Chicago chapter between the years of 1924 and 1992, though some of the material illustrates HEIB's activities on state and national levels as well. Documents in this collection contain information about HEIB's history, mission, membership, projects, and finances. The collection is divided into six series: General Information, Board Meeting Minutes, Newsletters, Finances, Projects, and State National Levels of HEIB. Material in each series is organized chronologically. Material in the collection includes meeting minutes, correspondence, newsletters, financial records, reports, project notes, speeches, budget proposals, and member lists.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Home Economists in Business --Archives.; Home economists --United States --Sources.
Midwest Women's History
Detailed Description/Box and Folder Listing
- Series I: General Information
  - Chicago group charter, HEIB history, 1924-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership lists, pamphlets, reports, 1928-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chicago group history, annual reports, 1948-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - HEIB objectives, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chairman's file, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership information, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Background information, by-laws, miscellaneous documents, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - HEIB Handbook, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - HEIB Handbook, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - HEIB Handbook, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - HEIB Handbook, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Membership Directory, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Local Group Handbook, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board Handbook, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series 2: Board Meeting Minutes
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - IHEA Executive Board--meeting minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - National HEIB--meeting minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, newsletters 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, newsletters, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Chicago HEIB and Executive Board--meeting minutes, officer lists, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, by-law amendments, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, objectives, treasurer's report, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting notices, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, by-law amendments, newsletters, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Chicago HEIB--meeting minutes, by-law amendments, newsletters, member list, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Series 3: Newsletters
  - Newsletters, correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters, correspondence, meeting minutes, member lists, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Newsletters, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Newsletters, correspondence, special project, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters, correspondence, membership information, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Newsletters, meeting minutes, budget reports, seminar program, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Newsletters, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Newsletters, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Newsletters, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Series 4: Finances
  - Budget proposal, financial reports, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Treasurer's reports, membership information, newsletters, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Financial statements, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Financial summaries, 1971-1983 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Financial records, check register, bank passbook, 1973-1982 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Budget requests, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Pamphlets, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Bank statements, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Brochure, correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Summary of Financial Activity, meeting minutes, reports, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Bank statements, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Treasurer's correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Treasurer's report, meeting minutes, by-laws, questionnaires, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Bank statements, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Bank statements, dues information, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Treasurer's report, newsletters, meeting minutes, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Financial summary, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Treasurer's report, year-end report, budget, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Treasurer's report, membership directory, meeting notices, newsletters, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Series 5: Projects
  - National Housing Center pamphlets, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Evanston Pilot Project, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Cookbook copyright, 1949-1957 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Evanston Township High School Home Economics Career Project, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Careers for Women: Special Recruitment Project, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Second Annual Careers for Women Conference, miscellaneous documents, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Local Group Workshop, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Local Group Workshop, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Job Placement, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Special Projects, Scholarship Program, Consumer Interest Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Membership Promotion, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Leadership in Action Workshop, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Leadership Breakfast, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Special Projects, miscellaneous documents, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Project with Cook County Public Aid, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Job Referral Service, questionnaires, newsletters, correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Pitfall Reports, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Special projects and program questionnaires, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Plan of Work and committee report, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 76)
- Series 6: State and National Levels of HEIB
  - National HEIB, Chicago HEIB, reports, clippings, meeting minutes, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - National HEIB, IHEA, IDA, miscellaneous documents, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - National HEIB, Chicago HEIB, reports, clippings, meeting minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - AHEA and HEIB convention, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - AHEA and IHEA, 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - IHEA, Chicago HEIB, correspondence, reports, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - AHEA and National Executive Board, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - IHEA and AHEA, miscellaneous dcuments, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - IHEA newsletters and reports, speeches, Chicago HEIB reports, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 85)
  - National HEIB, Planning Board meeting minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 86)
  - National HEIB, AHEA and IHEA, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 87)
  - IHEA--correspondence, newsletters, constitution, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 88)
  - National HEIB, AHEA, and IHEA 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 89)